So, in our data, since we have two rows for a company at least,
在这些数据中 同一家公司至少有两行数据
we have Year 1 and Year 2 data,
即第 1 年和第 2 年的数据
we are in a pickle if you just try to use match with one criteria,
所以 我们不能只用包含一个匹配标准的 Match 函数
because when we get to this,
因为 这样就无法
it's trying to match two criteria both the ticker symbol and the Year 1.
同时匹配股票代码和第 1 年这两个标准
So, this is where we will use Match with two criteria.
所以 在这种情况下 我们就要使用包含两个匹配标准的 Match 函数
For doing this, the Match function in Excel uses Boolean logic.
在 Excel 中使用此类 Match 函数时 需要运用布尔逻辑
If you're familiar with Boolean logic this will be straightforward.
如果你熟悉布尔逻辑 就很好理解了
Using Boolean logic, we can assign a variable,
运用布尔逻辑
a value of 1 when a particular condition is true and
就是当特定条件为真 则规定变量为 1
the variable is assigned a value of 0 if the condition is not met.
如果不符合条件 则规定变量为 0
So, let's first tackle the Boolean logic here.
首先 我们需要理清本例的布尔逻辑
We can see that the ticker symbol AVGO is true in the case of cell 1 and
股票代码 AVGO 在第 1 格和第 2 格为真
cell 2 which corresponds to the ticker symbol AVGO and the ticker symbol column here.
对应股票代码一列中的股票代码 AVGO
The value of Year 1 is true in the case of cell 1 or row 1,
而第 1 年的值分别在
3, 5, and 8.
第 1、3、5、8 行为真
But we want the condition of both ticker symbol AVGO and the
我们希望同时满足股票代码 AVGO 以及第 1 年均为真
Year 1 to be true which happens to be only in the case of row 1.
所以 只有第 1 行的值
So, this is when both the criteria are met.
同时满足这两个条件
So, I have indicated here with the true and false as well that these two are true.
我在这个区域标注了这两个条件的真与假 第一列中这两个值为真
But these are true in these rows,
而第二列中这些值均为真
but the combination of the two conditions is true only in this one, the first one,
但是只有在第一行 这两个条件同时为真
and this is the value that we want to pull out here and then for Year 2,
这就是我们想要提取的第 1 年数据
where the condition is met,
而当满足第 2 年的条件时
we'll have to pull it out here.
则提取值到这一格
So, we're saying match the condition when the value is 1.
我们想做的是 当值为 1 时匹配条件
So, we want both the conditions ticker symbol,
那就要同时满足
AVGO to be met,
第一个条件为股票代码 AVGO
which is row 1 as we know,
也就是第 1 行
and we want the second Year 1 value to be matched as well.
以及满足第二个条件 取第 1 年的值
So, only when both of these conditions are one,
只有当两个条件同时为 1
meet that condition exactly using,
完全满足整个条件
that's where the match type is zero and give us the location.
也就是这个函数中的查询方式为 0 时 返回相对位置
So, when we do this,
这个 Match 函数
we see that the value is 1.
所返回的值是 1
We want to plugin this particular value in the index function and say,
现在 我们要把这个具体值嵌入到 index 函数
"Give me the cost of revenue from the cost of revenue array when the row number is 1."
比如这里 当行号为 1 时 从营收成本的范围中提取对应的营收成本
So, I can show you this to be true.
我们来仔细看一下
I'm going to go back and actually put
把函数公式放在这里
this code here and you can actually see the formula.
供你参考
We're making both the condition to be true.
如果这两个条件均为真
What it does is, Excel does in the background is it calculates the, okay,
Excel 后台就会开始进行计算
when H1 equal to ticker symbol and it does the Boolean logic
按照布尔逻辑 当 H1 等于股票代码 (ticker symbol)
behind times when is a Boolean logic true for the years.
且年份为真
Multiply both of those conditions because it's assigning a value of 1 for
则将两个条件的布尔逻辑相乘
every true condition and 0 when the condition isn't met.
当条件为真时值为 1 而条件不符合时值为 0
So, it's multiplying both of those and it's giving
两个条件相乘之后
this final array and when this condition is met.
得出的最后范围是这样的
So, it's saying, "Okay.
可以看到
One match this condition exactly in the first location."
1 在第一个位置完全匹配这个条件
So, it gives us back the number 1.
因此返回的数字是 1
That is how you get the value for and total revenue.
这样就提取出总收入的值
We can repeat the process for all of her cells.
所有其他单元格同理操作
You have to type it in by hand, let me do that.
手动输入函数公式
So, we have total revenue,
对于总收入的范围
match it to the ticker symbol and to the F6 is year,
匹配股票代码和 F6 单元格的年份
give me the total revenue value when those conditions are met.
满足这些条件时 提取总收入的值
That's how you get the dashboard.
这样 表格就做好了
You can see that this is an interactive dashboard
这个表格还有交互性
because when you change the ticker symbol the value change.
因为 股票代码改变 相应的值就会随之改变
It's showing up as NA in the case of Year 3 because as you,
我们发现 第 3 年的数据显示为无效 (N/A)
let me show you this actual data.
这是因为 在实际数据中
As you can see, there's no Year 3 value except in the case of the HPE.
只有股票代码 HPE 有第 3 年数据
So, when you actually look at HPE,
如果把股票代码换成 HPE
that's when those values show up correctly.
所有的值就都能够正常显示
That's how you do a dashboard using index and matching.
关于如何用 Index 函数和 Match 函数将数据提取到表格中 我们就说到这里